בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is טז *Tet Zayin*. I
want to say a few minutes, a few seconds just to summarize
what we did yesterday because we're going to continue it today. We
had seen a very hard debate whether וסתות *vestos* are דאורייתא De'oraita
*de'oraisa* or דרבנן derabanan *de'rabbanan*, which means if a woman has a
regular period, do we, well first of all as I mentioned to
you,
we have to, there's a concern that she's going to see at
this time, so the couple can't have sex. That's discussed in גמרא
Gemara שבועות *Gemara Shavuos* and so on, that they have to be
פורש *poresh*, the couple cannot have sex during the days of the
expected period. The more focus of our discussion is what is her
status after that period passes, after that time passes. On the one
hand, she went into that time having the חזקת טהרה chazakas tahara
*chezkat tahara*, having the status of being טהורה tahora? *tehora*, but now
there's an expectation that that will change. Is that expectation strong enough
that to change her status quo? And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* frames
that as whether וסתות *vestos* are דאורייתא de-Oraisa. *de'oraisa*, is it biblical
or is it rabbinic? But now what biblical or rabbinic does a
general biblical principle of חזקה chazaka *chazaka* that we go by things
that have a pattern, like a pattern and habituation? So a woman
has habituation to see every time on the 30th day, that should
be significant. Yes, but the question is, so we know that it's
habitual, but is that habituation enough to say that it changes a
status quo and that now she switches without specific knowledge that that
actually has happened? Now, now there really are three possibilities. One is
טהורה tehorah. לגמרי *tehora legamre*, she's completely טהורה tehorah? *tehora*, she goes
by her status quo until we know otherwise. The other is she
is טמאה temeia *teme'ah*, she's completely considered טמאה temeia? *teme'ah*, the time
of her expected period passed and she's assumed to be definitely טמאה
temeia *teme'ah* unless there's absolute evidence otherwise. And of course there's a
middle possibility, it's a ספק safek *safek*, that this expectation was enough
to say that she's not definitely טהורה tehora *tehora* but not enough
to say she's טמאה temeia *teme'ah*, it puts her in a ספק
safek. *safek*. This actually, which of the positions were taken here, is
actually debated in the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* and I didn't spell this
out yesterday, so I want to clarify today because actually we had,
it had sounded like the beginning of the discussion of the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* that one said טמאה temeia *teme'ah*, the other said טהורה
tehora. *tehora*. It sounded like we were taking the absolute end of
the position, right? A husband comes home and has his wife, you
know, what does he assume has happened since because the time of
the period has passed, what assumptions can he make about his wife
and so on. But actually we ended with a position of רבי
Rabbi יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* which was in the middle, because what did
רבי Rabbi יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* say? רבי Rabbi יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said
it depends, has there been enough time for her to have gone
to the מקוה mikvah. *mikvah*. So he left on day 20, he
came back on day 40 since the last period. So the time
of her period passed but also enough time to go to the
מקוה mikvah. *mikvah*. So רבי Rabbi. יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said well, then
she can assume טהורה tehora *tehora*. And how did the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* explain this? Because maybe she saw, maybe she didn't see, and
on the other hand maybe she went to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah*,
maybe she didn't, there's a good chance she did, so therefore you
can combine the two and say that she is טהורה tehora, *tehora*.
So that shows that according to רבי Rabbi יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, the
fact that the period has passed makes her from definite טהור tahor.
*tahor* to ספק safek *safek*, right? Not definite טמא tamei *tamei*, but
to ספק safek *safek*, that's the assumption of רבי Rabbi, יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*. Therefore, since she's not definite טמא tamei, *tamei* and you don't
know she definitely went to the מקוה mikveh *mikvah* but a good
chance she did, you combine the two, assume she's טהורה tahora *tehora*.
So maybe, maybe it's a סברה *sevara*. Yeah, so it's not, she's
not a ספק safek, *safek*.
No, no, she is, you combine the fact that she is ספק
טמאה safek temeiah? *safek teme'ah*. She was what ספק טמאה safek temeiah
*safek teme'ah* 10 days ago, she is now maybe gone to the
מקוה mikvah, *mikvah* and that's enough that now 10 days later or
7 days later really that you can assume she's טהורה tehorah, *tehora*.
But the event of the passing of the period made her ספק
safek *safek*. So actually it is a מחלוקת ראשונים Rishonim *machlokes Rishonim*
which side רבי Rabbi, יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is taking. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*
says רבי Rabbi, יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is taking the side of וסתות
דרבנן vestot d'rabbanan, *vestos de'rabbanan*, that if you say וסתות דרבנן vestot
d'rabbanan. *vestos de'rabbanan* she is ספק safek? *safek*, and if you say
וסתות דאורייתא vestot d'oraita *vestos de'oraisa* she is ודאי טמאה vadai temeia.
*vadai teme'ah*. Okay, so according to תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, even according to
the position וסתות דרבנן vesetos de-rabbanan? *vestos de'rabbanan*, the assumption that she
is טהורה tehorah? *tehora* after the period has passed is only plus
waiting the seven days to assume that she has gone to the
מקוה mikvah *mikvah*. רשב"א *Rashba* and other ראשונים *Rishonim* take the opposite
position. No, if וסתות דרבנן vesetos de-rabbanan, *vestos de'rabbanan*, she's definitely טהורה
tehorah. *tehora*. You don't even have, you can come the next day,
the husband can come and you can assume she's definitely טהורה tehora,
*tehora*. Okay, there's a question when she's going to go for her
life without seeing, I mean fine, but whatever, but definitely טהורה tehora.
*tehora*. And if you say וסתות דאורייתא vestot d'oraita, *vestos de'oraisa*, that
makes her into a ספק *safek*. Okay, so that makes her, that's
enough to balance, to counterbalance the status quo of טהורה tehora. *tehora*
to make her into a ספק *safek*. Okay, so really what you
have is, right, you have three possibilities and which two are being
taken by the positions. According to תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, דרבנן d'rabbanan? *de'rabbanan*
means she's a ספק *safek*, it's enough to make it balance the
חזקה chazaka *chazaka*, דאורייתא *de'oraisa* means definitely טמאה temeiah, *teme'ah*, and according
to the other ראשונים *Rishonim*, no, דרבנן de-rabbanan *de'rabbanan* means you completely
keep her status quo, she's טהורה tehora. *tehora*, and דאורייתא *de'oraisa* means
she is a ספק *safek*. And the position of רבי Rabbi, יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* assumes that after this period she's a ספק *safek* and
if you wait a week, the husband waits a week, then he
can assume that she's gone to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah* and assume
she's טהורה tehora, *tehora* because that counterbalances her status of ספק *safek*.
Yeah, I don't understand why not just say as long as she's
the only
reliable,
right, so that is a big, you are absolutely. correct and that
is a big problem of this whole discussion which says בעלה the
husband comes home has sex with her but why doesn't he ask
her? And yes and as we pointed out all of this assumes
that I mean if you wanted to be nicer you could frame
it as
like here's a nicer way for it meaning the simple answer simple
answer one answer that's sometimes assumed in the גמרא Gemara is well
he's having sex with her while she's asleep and then the way
the ראשונים tone it down is well she's sort of awake but
not fully and she can't give a coherent answer which doesn't make
it so much better. Okay if you wanted I could make it
better than that a little bit better than that and say look
given the dynamics of the time and sometimes true even today the
wife might be if the husband comes home and says he wants
to have sex the wife might be embarrassed to say anything or
not have the courage to say I we can't I'm a נדה
niddah or whatever the pressures of the relationship the power dynamics and
so on. So to
actually it might actually be that the woman doesn't always feel free
to say what it is so we have to sort of bespeak
about these realities about those types of things but of course the
response to that would be that by speaking about it and telling
him what he can or can't do without asking his wife it
feeds into that. So I don't have a good answer the really
but the assumption is that the גמרא Gemara is reflecting realities that
sometimes husbands would not ask their wives and you had but it's
yeah it really is disturbing.
Two questions and if אין לה ווסת ein la vesset according to
everybody everyone it's okay?
Yes אין לה ווסת ein la vesset is okay although as we're
going to see a little bit in a few minutes there's going
to be a question about a pseudo ווסת vesset of thirty days
for women that אין לה ווסת. ein la vesset.
And then beforehand and meaning if beforehand there's no issue she has
a חזקה chazaka. according to everybody it is okay. So then but
why can't it just like ר' מאיר Reb Meir who always חייש
למיעוטא chaish lemi'uta say well יש לה ווסת yesh la vesset whatever
maybe she was a זבה zava in which case she may not
be טהורה?
tehora, No no no no no because you have a חזקה chazaka.
what do you mean? You have a חזקת טהרה chazakas tahara ר'
מאיר Reb Meir isn't חייש chaish no
no meaning before the ווסת vesset when you left you came back
after the ווסת vesset but maybe depending on when you came back
she could have been a זבה. zava.
Maybe a million things but as long as you're not חייש למיעוטא?
chaish lemi'uta? No I'm not going to do with ר' מאיר'ס Reb
Meir's חזקה. chazaka, You have a חזקת טהרה chazakas tahara. unless you
have an absolute prediction that something is going to change we don't
change the חזקת טהרה. Okay so that's what we did yesterday. So
anyway the גמרא Gemara now focuses on the second this second part
of the status. We're going to get back to ווסתות vessetot in
a minute but the גמרא Gemara now focuses on this second part
of the status which as the second part of the discussion which
is if she was definitely טמאה temeia. you could not assume she
went to the מקוה. mikvah, It's only because as I say she's
ספק whether it's דאורייתא or דרבנן that you could assume that she
went to the מקוה. mikvah.
What do you mean if she was טמאה? temeia.
If the husband left but she was טמאה temeia or she was
childbirth or whatever knew definite and that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's idea of
אין ספק מוציא מידי וודאי. ein safek motzi midei vadai. Now of
course אין ספק מוציא מידי וודאי ein safek motzi midei vadai right?
If it's definitely one thing you can't say well maybe. But the
point is it's not just any ספק. This is like there's a
pretty good chance pretty much expect that his wife is going to
go to the מקוה mikvah he just doesn't know for sure. So
can we say that ספק is מוציא מידי וודאי motzi midei vadai
when there was a status but there's a pretty good chance it
changed? So now the גמרא Gemara is going to continue with this
and we finally and we resume and we pick up about six
eight lines from the
bottom ט"ו ע"ב. Tes-Vav Amud Beis. והשתא דאמרת אין ספק מוציא מידי
וודאי ve-hashta de-amart ein safek motzi midei vadai we're in the sort
of parenthesis with the asterisk. Still are you is your claim that
a ספק cannot change the status of a וודאי vadai a previous
status? והתניא ve-hatanya we taught in the ברייתא Braisa מעשה בשפחתו של
מסיק אחד ברימון ma'aseh b'shifchato shel Masik echad b'Rimmon there was a
story with the slave servant of a מסיק Masik which could mean
an olive presser or could mean a strong man מסיק Masik depending
on how you interpret we'll see the story in רימון Rimmon which
was a place שהטילה נפל לבור she-hetilah nefel le-bor that she had
a miscarriage and she threw the fetus into a pit ובא כהן
והציץ בו לידע אם זכר אם נקבה u-ba Kohen ve-hitzitz bo leyda
im zachar im nekeva and the כהן Kohen went and peeked over
like humped over the pit looked over the pit to see whether
it was a male or female to see whether this maidservant was
how long she was טמאה temeia. for seven days or fourteen days.
How could he do that? He's a כהן. Kohen. So there's a
whole discussion. Some say because the guy was because the guy was
a strong like a violent person so he forced the כהן Kohen
some say that the כהן Kohen was a קטן katan although that
doesn't really answer it because a קטן katan isn't allowed to become
טמא tamei either and adults are מצווה metzuve for making קטנים ketanim
טמאים. temeim. So but nevertheless there was some pressure.
Perhaps he was having sex with her anyway?
No no because she's handling תרומה terumah maybe? She could still become
טמאה temeia. right? Because she's handling תרומה terumah and so the best
answer רש"י Rashi says is that he was just he didn't know
better he was an עם הארץ am ha'aretz he didn't care about
הלכה. halacha. But anyway so the כהן Kohen came to look over
ובא מעשה לפני חכמים וטהרוהו u-ba ma'aseh lifnei Chachamim ve-tiharu'u
and the case came before the חכמים Chachamim and they said the
כהן Kohen is טהור. tahor, He didn't see anything obviously is the
point.
מפני שחולדה וברקתא מצויין שם mipnei she-chulda u-varka metzuyin sham
because weasels and I don't know what these are weasels and something
else that's like a weasel are found there. You'll tell me what
the English says these animals are. What? Anyway, whatever, various types of
scurrying burrowing animals are there, so you didn't see anything we can
assume that they just picked it up and buried under his feet.
Okay, but still we've got a problem. והכא דודאי הטילה נפל, vehacha
devaday hetilah nefel, that definitely it was there. ספק גררו ספק לא
גררו, safek geraru safek lo geraru, maybe it was dragged away, maybe
it wasn't. Now it's not just a maybe, there's a little supporting
evidence, which is you didn't see it. Okay, fine, but it's still
not a וודאי. vaday. There's a good chance it was dragged away,
but not a וודאי. vaday. וקאתי ספק ומוציא מידי וודאי, vekasi safek
umotzi miyedei vaday, and that definite is and that doubt is coming
and it's changing a וודאי vaday status. Now I will tell you
this is a little different because here there's another וודאי. vaday. The
כהן kohen has a status called being טהור, tahor right? So the
גמרא Gemara put a factor that in as opposed to the טבל
tevel was דמאי demai you want to eat the טבל. tevel. The
woman was a נדה niddah now they want to have sex. Here
the כהן kohen was טהור tahor, even though the thing was definitely
there. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara doesn't factor that in. It says why
is the ספק מוציא מידי וודאי? safek motzi miyedei vaday? So the
גמרא Gemara says לא תימא דהטילה נפל לבור, lo seima dehetilah nefel
labor, don't say that she threw something which is a definite fetus
into the pit, אלא אימא ela eima 16a-1 כמי נפל, kimi nefel,
it was possibly a fetus, meaning it wasn't clear. Different types of
based on the nature of the miscarriage it might not even be
considered to have the status of a מת. meis. So it wasn't
clear whether it really was just some type of discharge or was
it really a נפל. nefel. So the גמרא Gemara says so therefore
it was it wasn't a definite problem to begin with. So the
גמרא Gemara says והא לידה זכר ונקבה תני, veha leida zachar unekeivah
tani, but it says know if it was male or female, which
assumes that it definitely was a fetus. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this
is what it means. ובא כהן והטביל ועלה וראה אם נפל הפילה
או רוח הפילה. uba kohen vehitbil ve'alah vera'ah im nefel hipila o
ruach hipila. First he wanted to determine whether it was a real
fetus in the in the embryonic sac or not,
ואי תימצא לומר נפל הפילה, ve'im timtza lomar nefel hipila,
and if it really was a fetus, then לידע אם זכר אם
נקבה, leida im zachar im nekeivah, you want to know male or
female. But first thing he had to establish was that it was
a fetus. So it wasn't definitely a problem to begin with. ואיבעית
אימא, ve'iba'is eima, if you want you could say, כיון דחולדה וברדלס
מצויים שם, keivan dechuldah uvardelas metzuyim sham, since the weasel and whatever
it was were there, what's another burrowing animal? Mole,
a mole rat? Polecat? Polecat. Okay. Anyway, since they are there, וודאי
גררו, vaday geraru, it's so definite that we can say they definitely
dragged it, maybe also with supporting evidence that he didn't see anything.
So this is the point, right? We'll say אין ספק מוציא מידי
וודאי ein safek motzi miyedei vaday unless the likelihood is so high,
no, but it's not really a וודאי, vaday, but it's so high
that we're prepared to consider it a וודאי. vaday. So the way
we say that the possibilities that something changed override is either if
we say that we didn't start out with it being a definite
problem like the man didn't know his wife had definitely become a
נדה niddah or the likelihood is so high that it's if it's
definite even though it's not a hundred percent. Okay. It's worth pointing
out before we now transition back to the other discussion about ווסת
דאורייתא, vessest de'oraisa, that I summarized for you at the beginning, that
this often is also described as a חזקה. chazaka Not חזקה, chazaka
you could say
חזקה חולדה וברדלס chazaka chuldah uvardelas and
drag anything that they find. But often חזקה chazaka is also used
by sort of human nature. It's a חזקה chazaka that a woman
would always go to the מקוה as soon as she's able. חזקה
chazaka that a חבר chaver does not leave his grain without taking
תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros. So sometimes חזקה chazaka is used to
describe well-established patterns of behavior. And things that so that's a very
different חזקה chazaka than a status quo. Like a woman has a
חזקה chazaka of being טהורה. tehora The grain has a חזקה chazaka,
of being טבל. tevel. That's just whatever the status quo is we
assume that status quo remains. So in a way, part of this
question is, can a something that has the status quo, the woman
was טמאה, temeia. the grain was טבל, tevel, be overridden by a
חזקה by a like an established pattern of behavior? Is that strong
enough to assume that it changed the status? So that's another way
of framing it but that's not the way the גמרא Gemara doesn't
use the phrase חזקה, it says וודאי vaday and ספק, and in
the end we'll let the ספק change it when it's strong enough
that we consider it to be a וודאי. vaday. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara goes back to the discussion of ווסת דאורייתא vessest de'oraisa
which I summarized for you at the beginning. Let's take a look.
Okay, בעי מיניה רב נחמן. ba'ei mineih Rav Nachman. They asked Rav
Nachman, again, about six lines from the top. ווסת דאורייתא או דרבנן?
vessest de'oraisa o derabanan? So there we go, we're now being reintroduced
to this discussion. Is the idea of when a woman expects to
get her period at a fixed date, is that considered to have
biblical weight or to be rabbinic? And as I said, meaning is
after that period passes, is she considered to be, one way of
framing the debate is וודאי טמאה vaday temeiah or ספק טמאה? safek
temeia Another way of framing the debate is is she considered after
that to be ספק טמאה temeia or טהורה? tehora. There are three
possibilities, the question is which two of these occupy? Anyway, so what's
the story, biblical or rabbinic? אמר ליה, amar lei, he said, מכדי
דאמר הונא חבריין משמיה דרב. michdi de'amar Huna chavrayan mishmeih deRav. Since
Huna
our friend said in the name of Rav, אשה שיש לה ווסת,
ishah sheyeish lah vessest, a woman who has a regular period, והגיע
שעת ווסתה, vehigia she'as vesstah, that time occurred, ולא בדקה, velo badkah,
and she did not check herself during the time of her period,
ולסוף ראתה, ulesof ra'asah, and then later she saw, a day later
she saw that she was bleeding, okay, and she didn't bleed. חבריא
משמיה דרב הונא, Chavraya mishmei de-Rav Huna, since הונא Huna our friend
said in the name of רב, Rav, אשה שיש לה וסת, isha
sheyesh la vest, a woman who has a regular period, והגיע שעת
וסתה, vehigia she'at vesta, that time occurs, ולא בדקה, velo badka, and
she did not check herself during the time of her period, ובסוף
ראתה, uvesof raata, and then later she saw, a day later she
saw that she was bleeding, okay, and she didn't check herself from
the time of her period until whatever it is, a day later,
an hour later, whatever it is, חוששת לוסתה וחוששת לראייתה. chosheshat levista
vechosheshat lereiyata.
She has to be concerned number one that she saw on the
time of her וסת, veset,
and she has to be concerned for her when she actually saw.
She doesn't know when she saw. So maybe she saw now, I
mean she knows she saw now, okay, but it's also possible that
it happened when her וסת veset period occurred. So therefore she has
to be concerned both ways. What does it mean concerned both ways?
On the one hand, anything that she handled from the time of
her וסת veset until now, she has to be concerned that at
the time of her וסת veset she had her period and she
was טמאה. temeia So she has to be concerned about anything she
might have handled from that time on. What does it mean to
be concerned that it's only now? I mean if you're concerned that
it was two days ago or two hours ago, of course you're
concerned now, she knows she's טמאה. temeia. Well, right, the one thing
is when she's counting her when she can go to the מקוה,
she can't go to the מקוה from yesterday which was her וסת,
veset, she can only go to the מקוה counting seven days from
today. The other related point is not only when she can go
to the מקוה, but when she has to establish you know, when
she assumes if the next time she bleeds is she a נדה,
niddah, is she a זבה? zavah? So the day that she actually
saw her period is very important for establishing the future of what
her cycle is and what her period is and when she can
go to the מקוה. So both days are possibilities and she has
to be concerned for both days. Now what does that prove? What
do you think that proves? Is וסתות דאורייתא vestot d'oraita, or דרבנן?
You don't think it proves anything. Okay, let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says. That was a good answer. All right,
anyways, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
עלמא, Alma, you see וסתות דאורייתא, vestot d'oraita that they're biblical. Why?
Because the גמרא's Gemara assuming and obviously why is it assuming that's
your answer correctly reflected that it that this case would have been
the we would have been concerned for the day of her period
even had she not bled now. We would have treated her טמאה
temeia from that day. Of course that's not said, it's said that
now that she's bled we retroactively are concerned from that day. But
the גמרא Gemara assumes that the now that she's bled was not
relevant and therefore it tries to prove that וסתות דאורייתא, vestot d'oraita.
but the גמרא Gemara quickly rejects that. The גמרא Gemara says איכא
דאמרי ika d'amri some say הכי קאמר ליה, hachi ka'amar lei, that
this is what he tried to prove from this case. טעמא דראתה,
Taama d'raata, the reason that we are concerned back to the day
of her וסת veset is that she saw today. הא לא ראתה,
Ha lo raata, had she not seen today, אין חוששין, ein chosheshin,
we would not be concerned to consider her טמאה. temeia. Just because
the day passed we're not saying oh now she's טמאה. teme'ah, Once
she bleeds then maybe we'll worry backwards, but until that prime happens
we're not now considering her טמאה. teme'ah, עלמא, Alma, you
see וסתות דרבנן, vesetos de-rabbanan. you see it's only rabbinic. Now what
does that mean? Rabbinic and therefore she's טהורה tehorah or rabbinic and
therefore she's ספק? Again that exactly is not clear but regardless the
point is is that do you assume that as soon as the
day passed you'd treat it as טמאה t'meah or no only once
now we know that she's טמאה t'meah? and that is not clear
from that and therefore as you all correctly said that ברייתא braita
was inconclusive.
So basically he asked the question he didn't really give an answer.
Correct.
איתמר, Itmar, so now we're going to keep on working on this.
אשה שיש לה וסת, isha sheyesh la veset, והגיע שעת וסתה, vehigia
she'at vesta, ולא בדקה. velo badka. So her time came of her
regular period and she did not check. ובסוף בדקה, uvasof badka,
and she checked later, an hour later, whatever she checked. אמר רב,
Amar Rav, so here what's the הלכה? halakha? So רב Rav says
בדקה ומצאת טמאה טמאה, badka umatzat temeia temeia, טהורה טהורה. tahora tahora.
Oh that makes a lot of sense.
If she checked and she's now bleeding, okay, then she's טמאה. t'meah,
And you know what? Maybe she's even טמאה t'meah, retroactively from the
time who knows. But the key really is the next statement. Okay,
anyway the whole retroactive only matters for טהרות, taharos, anyway the key
is the next statement. If she checks and she's not bleeding now,
she can assume that she is still טהורה. tehorah And she doesn't
have to say that just because the וסת veset period passed she's
already considered ספק טמאה t'meah. or ודאי טמאה. t'meah, No, you can
check afterwards and if now you're טהורה tehorah. that is strong enough
to assume that the וסת veset did not make her that it
she did not get her period. Okay, so that is clearly a
principle of וסתות דרבנן. vesetos de-rabbanan. ושמואל אמר, u-Shmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel
says I don't see that either.
I mean because in other words even if וסתות דאורייתא vesetos de-Oraisa
she's
going to for sure happen, let's see what שמואל Shmuel says. ושמואל
אמר u-Shmuel amar אפילו בדקה ומצאת טהורה נמי טמאה. afilu badka umatzat
tehora nami temeia. Even if she checks now afterwards and she finds
she's טהורה, tehorah, נמי טמאה, nami temeia, you have to assume she's
טמאה. t'mea, Why? מפני שאורח בזמנו בא. mipnei she'oreiach bizmano ba. The
guest comes at his at at its appointed time. Right isn't there
some phrase about calling the the period the monthly visitor or something
like that? Yeah. So the visitor comes on at you know at
its appointed schedule which is another way of saying or seems to
be saying וסתות דאורייתא. vesetos de-Oraisa, Now Michael is saying what do
you mean you have counter evidence that you checked? Ah but the
גמרא Gemara is assumes that if you can check to prove she's
טהורה tehora but you have to be checking during the time and
the of the וסת. veset. It's important to realize that I've been
describing it to you like she's expecting day twenty-eight. According to the
גמרא Gemara you don't have a וסת veset for a whole day.
You basically have a וסת veset for a half a day like
the daytime of the twenty-eighth day or the nighttime of the twenty-eighth
day. It actually and even there that seems to be the less
regular וסת veset the way the גמרא Gemara imagines it. The גמרא
Gemara imagines... a very precise ווסת. veset. And because the גמרא Gemara.
probably imagined and seems later that the גמרא Gemara that a ווסת
veset standard ווסת veset is a ווסת הגוף, veset haguf, not about
a twenty-eight day cycle, but let's say it's actually something that when
a woman gets menstrual cramps and bleeding always accompanies those cramps, that
could be a ווסת veset as well. So there actually is possible
to pinpoint the time. Right now you're getting these cramps, this is
your time of your ווסת. veset. So if a woman checks throughout
that period of cramping or, you know, then or let's say during
the daytime she's expecting to check during the time she's expecting and
she's טהורה, tehora. then it's absolute one hundred percent evidence she did
not bleed during the time of her ווסת. veset. But the גמרא
Gemara assumes that if the checking is after that period, even three
hours later, whatever, an hour later, but whatever, then you don't know,
maybe the bleeding occurred, you're now checking not at the relevant time,
you're checking after the relevant time. So maybe she bled during the
relevant time and maybe you know as I said they weren't wearing
tight-fitting underwear whatever got absorbed into her clothes or whatever, and a
check now does not really prove whether she had a period, whether
she had any blood during the previous period. So that's why the
גמרא Gemara says a check afterwards is not absolute proof. It's good
supporting evidence, but it's not absolute proof. And therefore if ווסתות דאורייתא,
vestot de'oraita, it is not enough to be a counterproof to the
assumption that she bled during that period.
See if she's wearing like, you know, something completely laundered and it
would show.
No, that would, that might be considered like a proof or whatever,
although again it's a problem because you have to do an internal
check and that's external, but let's not get with the, you know,
exceptional cases. I'm trying to give you the general assumptions of the
גמרא. Gemara Yes.
Is this a momentary check or something like a מוך? moch?
So that's the issue. Meaning right, it gets confusing nowadays because this
גמרא Gemara is applied
to our reality where most normally women have a ווסת veset for
like an entire twelve hour period, like some time during their daytime.
So the often the הלכה halacha will be said is, oh, she
should check sometime during her ווסת. veset. But that's crazy because maybe
she checked in the morning and it's going to happen later in
the day. What could it, if anything it makes sense to check
after the ווסת. veset. So you'll get some opinions like, okay, she
ideally she should have, she should have a tampon in for the
entire twelve hour period. Or you know anyway it's, but that's why
it's important to understand that the גמרא Gemara is talking about a
more narrow like like during menstrual cramps. Like there's a very a
limited finite period, you know, a small period that she can check
for. I see. I understand. But yeah, I'm working with the assumption,
and how this translates הלכה למעשה halacha lema'aseh is a separate discussion,
that the בדיקה bedikah is during the entire period, it's a small
period and during the entire period that she's expecting, so it's definite
proof otherwise.
Meaning any point during that period. No.
Oh, yes, which is why I'm assuming that or it could mean
like an inserted tampon or whatever. Okay, whatever, I don't want to
get into it. It's obviously possible to read the גמרא Gemara otherwise
but then the question is if it's not, if it's only for
a limited time, what good is what how big of a proof
is this? And why is checking after not at least as good
as checking for five minutes during? So I'm working with the assumption
that we're talking about during the entire period, it's a short period
or it's about some type of a something inserted that leaves there
and so on. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says according to שמואל Shmuel
that even with a good check she's טמאה, t'mea proves that ווסתות
vestot are, well the גמרא Gemara hasn't said it yet, so let's
read what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So שמואל Shmuel says אורח בזמנו בא. oreach bizmano ba.
Okay, the visitor comes at its time. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara, says. לימא בווסתות קמיפלגי. leima bevestot kamiflegi. It sounds like
they're debating this ווסתות vestot question. מר סבר דאורייתא ומר סבר דרבנן.
mar savar de'oraita umar savar derabbanan. One holds it's biblical, one holds
it's rabbinic. And therefore the difference is due to a, is a
good check afterwards enough to say that she's טהורה? אמר רבי זירא,
amar Rabbi Zeira, לא דכולי עלמא ווסתות דאורייתא. lo dechulei alma vestot
de'oraita.
Everybody could really say that ווסתות vestot are biblical. Really? So why
does according to רב Rav the check afterwards work? כאן בבדקה עצמה
בתוך שיעור ווסת כאן בלא בדקה עצמה בתוך שיעור ווסת. kan bevadkah
atzmah betoch shiur veset kan belo vadkah atzmah betoch shiur veset. Maybe
they're not disagreeing, they're talking about different scenarios. If she checked בתוך
שיעור ווסת, betoch shiur veset, again that word ווסת veset plays double
duty. שיעור ווסת shiur veset means like immediately afterwards, a few seconds
afterwards. So according to רב, Rav, if she checked, if she checked
two seconds after the ווסת veset was over, that's just as good
as checking during the ווסת. veset. So that's like she checked during
the ווסת veset and therefore it works and she's טהורה. It's like
direct proof she didn't bleed during the ווסת. veset. According to שמואל,
Shmuel, she checked more than two seconds afterwards. So therefore even though
it's clean, maybe she bled during the ווסת veset and the blood
went away or got lost or something of that nature. So they
really agree that the assumption is טמאה, ווסתות דאורייתא vestot de'oraita unless
you have absolute proof. The question is when can you check to
make absolute proof. During the period? I discussed whatever you know, maybe
it's throughout the period, maybe not, whatever, but during the period, or
up to one or two seconds after is good. But more than,
and רב Rav was maybe talking within one or two seconds after,
more than two seconds after doesn't prove anything and that's what שמואל
Shmuel was talking about. That's one way of framing it. רב נחמן
בר יצחק אמר, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar, רב נחמן
בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said, בווסתות גופייהו קמיפלגי. bevestot gufaihu
kamiflegi. No, of course they're debating the ווסתות vestot issue.
מר סבר ווסתות דאורייתא. mar savar vestot de'oraita. שמואל Shmuel holds that
ווסתות vestot are biblical and
therefore even a later check doesn't is not enough. אמר רב ששת
*Amar Rav Sheshes*, says רב ששת *Rav Sheshes*, כתנאי *ki-tannai*. This is
this is actually a debate of תנאים *Tannaim*. רבי אליעזר אומר טמאה
נדה Niddah, *Rabbi Eliezer omer tameiah niddah*. A woman we're assuming it
doesn't tell us the context, but we're assuming it's the same context.
A woman who checked after her וסת veses *veses*. So רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer* says she is considered like a נדה Niddah *niddah*. Well,
again, that sounds like by the way that and now it sounds,
by the way, as I said before, that according to the approach
of וסתות דאורייתא vesetos de-Oraisa. *vestos d'Oraisa*, I mean, definitely טמאה *tameiah*.
Right? A, that's the language of נדה Niddah *niddah*. He doesn't say
ספק *safek*, he says נדה Niddah, *niddah*. And the whole assumption in
this דף *daf* seems to be that if וסתות דאורייתא vestos de'oraissa
*vestos d'Oraisa*, if a check later isn't strong enough to counteract it,
it sounds like וסתות דאורייתא *vestos d'Oraisa* means definitely טמאה *tameiah*. So
one opinion is נדה Niddah. *niddah*, וסתות דאורייתא *vestos d'Oraisa*, definitely טמאה
*tameiah*. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, אומר תיבדק *Rabbi Yehoshua omer tibadek*! No,
let's check, have her check, and we'll find out. Which sounds like
וסתות דרבנן vesetos de-rabbanan. *vestos d'Rabbanan*. You do a check afterwards and
that will determine. So maybe it's a ספק *safek* and a check
later will determine it for you. Okay. So that is and he
understands that that is the debate of וסתות דאורייתא *vestos d'Oraisa*. דהני
תנאי כהני תנאי *De-hani tannai ke-hani tannai*. This debate of תנאים *Tannaim*
is like the following debate דתניא *de-tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא
Baraisa *Beraisa*. רבי מאיר אומר טמאה נדה Niddah? *Rabbi Meir omer tameiah
niddah*. That a again, assuming the same scenario, a woman checked after
her וסת veses *veses*. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says she's a definitely
ודאי טמאה *vadai tameiah*,
she's a נדה Niddah, *niddah*. וחכמים אומרים תיבדק *Ve-chachamim omrim tibadek*. Check!
She's doubtfully טמאה *tameiah*, וסתות דרבנן vesetos de-rabbanan. *vestos d'Rabbanan*, check. אמר
אביי *Amar Abaye*, אף אנן נמי תנינא *af anan nami tanina*. We
also taught implicitly this in a משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* that רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* says וסתות דאורייתא *vestos d'Oraisa*. How do you know? דתנן
*de-tannan*, it's taught in a משנה mishna. *Mishnah*: רבי מאיר אומר *Rabbi
Meir omer*, אם הייתה במחבא *im hayesa be-machava*, we quoted this before,
if a woman was in a cave and hiding from bandits or
whatever, והגיע שעת וסתה *ve-higia she'as vestah*, and the time of her
period comes, ולא בדקה *ve-lo badkah*, and she did not check, טהורה
*tehorah*. She can still assume that she's טהורה *tehorah* in this case.
Why? שחרדה מסלקת את הדמים *she-charada mesalekes es ha-damim*. The fear causes
her to not bleed. This is the idea of מסולקת דמים mesulekes
damim, *mesulekes damim* which we talked about before pregnant, post-menopausal. Here רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says fear does the same. Now what does that
prove? הגמרא *Ha-Gemara* says it proves the following: טעמא דאיכא חרדה *ta'ama
de-ika charada*, we assume that she is טהורה *tehorah* because she is
because there's a fear. הא ליכא חרדה *ha leika charada*, if she
is if there's not fear, טמאה *tameiah*, we would assume she's טמאה
*tameiah*. And therefore אלמא וסתות דאורייתא *alma vestos d'Oraisa*. You see it's
biblical. Now, it's not exactly clear why that proves anything. Maybe if
there is no fear, she has to check, she's ספק *safek*. How
do we know she's definitely טמאה *tameiah*? So תוספות Tosafos. *Tosafos* tries
to figure out exactly what the proof of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is, but nevertheless this seems to be now clear as opposed to
my introduction, which, you know, but now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems
to be sort of clear that, you know, although there was a
debate of ראשונים *Rishonim* before exactly how to read רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* and the possibility of going to the מקוה *mikveh* and so
on, here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to be very clear that
if וסתות דאורייתא *vestos d'Oraisa*, after the time passes she's definitely טמאה
*tameiah*, and even a good check won't counteract that. The only way
for her to prove that she's טהורה *tehorah* is to have checked
during the period. Whatever. And if וסתות דרבנן vesetos de-rabbanan. *vestos d'Rabbanan*,
then after the period passes she's a ספק *safek*, she's doubtful, and
a later check will be able to prove that she is טהורה
*tehorah*. And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wraps this up. לימא הני
תנאי *Leima hani tannai*, let's say these תנאים *Tannaim* בהכי נמי פליגי
*be-hacha nami peligi*, that the following תנאים *Tannaim* also are part of
this same debate, דתניא *de-tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא Braitia. *Beraisa*:
הרואה דם dam, מחמת מכה makkah *Ha-ro'ah dam machamas makah*. Now, again,
very important about, you know, a woman who's bleeding and determining that
it's coming from some internal type of a, you know, wound or
something, or some type of medical condition, and it's not blood of
נדה Niddah. *niddah*. So the question is under what circumstances can you,
a, assess that it's coming from a wound? Like here it says
a woman who's bleeding from a wound. How do we know? Right?
So that's one question, which I'm not going to get into. But
whatever, we're assuming that we know or there's good evidence to support
that, and אפילו בתוך ימי נדה Niddah. פירש טהורה *afilu besoch yemei
niddah peiresh tehorah*. This is רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*. Even during the
period of her נדה Niddah *niddah* she's טהורה *tehorah*. Now, it doesn't
mean she's actually has had her menstrual bleeding and she's טהורה *tehorah*
because then why would she be טהורה *tehorah* just because she's also
bleeding from a wound? But it means even when we expect that
this is her menstrual period, even after her וסת veses *veses* has
passed, since she's טהורה *tehorah*, why? Because we assume the blood we're
seeing, we know, could definitely or could, and maybe is definitely coming
from the מכה makkah *makah*. So the only question is maybe there's
blood of נדה Niddah *niddah* mixed up with it. That maybe is
not going to be enough to assume
she's going to be טמאה *tameiah*. We assume she's טהורה *tehorah* even
after the time of her period passes. Okay,
that's what
רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says. What? Wait a minute. They say until
now we've been saying that it's a ספק *safek* and you need
a good check. Here we're saying that she's completely טהורה *tehorah*. So
the basic answer is what's the difference? Why here do you not
need a check?
Because you can't do a check.
So the רמב"ן *Ramban* makes that point. Yeah, he says the idea
that you would need a check is basically a rabbinic requirement. If
this woman has a מכה makkah, *makah* and there's no way to
determine it, we're going to waive the rabbinic requirement. We're not going
to make her so therefore she is going to remain טהורה *tehorah*
because the basic principle, if וסתות דרבנן *vestos d'Rabbanan*, and this goes
back to what I also what I said
in the
beginning, is that really she's טהורה לגמרי *tehorah le-gamrei*. And he'd be
מותר to her husband? Yes. Now, of course
the question then the תוספות Tosafos raise, or what we'll see in
the גמרא Gemara. the תוספות Tosafos raise, is דהכי לעולם לא תהיה.
de-hacha le-olam lo tihye. Right? I mean, what do you mean, that
she's for ten years she's never going to be a נדה, niddah?
she's got to have her period at some point? So I'll talk
about that in a minute, but what's your question?
Can we also mention that the blood might be of a different
quality?
Yeah, but that's, so sometimes you check for that, but let's bracket
that. Okay, let's assume when you have to check or when that
makes an issue, but that's a factor, but we're going to bracket
that for now. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shim'on says yeah, so even if the period passes,
טהורה, no way to check, טהורה. רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, רבי says,
אם יש לה וסת חוששת לוסתה. im yesh la veses chosheshes le-vistah.
Now, if she has a regular period, she has to be concerned
about her regular period. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו בהא
קמיפלגי, ma'i lav ha' kamifligi, it seems to be the debate, דמר
סבר וסת דאורייתא ומר סבר וסת דרבנן. de-mar savar veses de-oraisa u-mar
savar veses de-rabbanan. Right?
One says she's definitely טמאה and the other says she's not, and
because of the מכה makkah. no way to check and therefore she's
טהורה. That seems to be exactly the debate. אמר רבינא לא, Amar
Ravina lo, not necessarily, דכולי עלמא וסת דרבנן. de-kulei alma veses de-rabbanan.
They'd all say that the וסת veses. is דרבנן and therefore in
this case of the מכה makka, she really should be טהורה. והכא,
Ve-hacha,
and really the debate is about something totally else and he's going
to read this משנה, mishna this ברייתא in a way you never
would have expected. והכא, Ve-hacha, here's the way to read the debate:
במקור, be-makor, if it was just a question is is she טמאה?
The answer is no, she's not טמאה, there's blood of a מכה,
makka we have no way of knowing there's blood of a נדה
niddah mixed in with it or not, even though her וסת veset
passed, וסת דרבנן veses de-rabbanan she's not טמאה, she's טהורה, everybody agrees.
So what's the debate? והכא במקור מקומו טמא קמיפלגי. Ve-hacha bi-m'kor m'komo
tamei ka mifligi.
They debate whether the uterus, the מקור, makor, the uterus is, its
place is טמא, tamei? which means, obviously this is a disturbing conceptual
idea,
but just halakhically what that means is a woman only becomes a
נדה niddah when she has menstrual bleeding from the uterus. But let's
say there's a wound in the uterus and there's blood there that
we can all agree is not menstrual blood. She is not going
to be a נדה, Niddah. that does not make her as a
person a נדה. Niddah. The question is is the blood טמא tamei?
just for laws of like תרומה, terumah, not for her status of
a נדה? For law, you know, all other הלכות halakhos of טומאה
וטהרה, tumah ve-taharah, is the blood טמא? tamei Is blood that has
passed through, touched the inside of the uterus טמא? tamei, Since the
uterine blood makes her נדה, maybe the uterus makes any blood into
טמא tamei even though it didn't make her a נדה. That's the
question. So how does that fit into the discussion here? Here's the
way he wants to read the discussion. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר סבר
אשה טהורה, Rabbi Shim'on ben Elazar savar isha tehora, so remember, everybody
says וסת דרבנן, veses de-rabbanan, so the woman we're all going to
agree is טהורה, she doesn't is not assumed to have menstrual bleeding.
But at the, nevertheless there's still blood that came from the uterus,
what's the status of this blood? So he says if she's טהורה
הדם טמא, ha-dam tamei, but the blood is טמא, tamei דקאתי דרך
מקור, de-ka'asi derech makor, it came from the uterus even though it
wasn't menstrual blood, even though it wasn't the uterine lining, even though
it was wound blood, it still is טמא tamei, without her being
a נדה. ואמרי ליה רבי, Ve-amre lei Rabbi,
so רבי says back to him, remember, רבי was the one who
sounded like he was being strict, he said if she has a
וסת veset she's concerned for her וסת. veset, So now here's how
we're going to re-read רבי. So רבי says אי חיישת לוסת, i
chayshas le-veses, look,
if you wanted to be concerned about her period then אשה נמי
טמאה, isha nami t'meah, you should have said that she was טמאה.
Okay, if you want to be concerned about her period. Obviously you're
not concerned about her period cause you said that she's טהורה. So
then be consistent: אי לא חיישת לוסת, i lo chayshas le-veses, if
you're not going to be concerned about her period because וסת דרבנן,
veses de-rabbanan, it's how he's re-reading רבי, therefore מקור מקומו טהור הוא,
m'kor m'komo tahor hu, then the blood is also going to be
טהור, there's no idea that the blood is טמא tamei and she
is not. So since we're not going to be concerned about her
period because וסת דרבנן, veses de-rabbanan, it's how it's re-reading רבי, therefore
the blood is also not going to be טמא, tamei? the only
reason blood would be טמא tamei, is if it is blood of
נדה not just because it was in the uterus. Now obviously there's,
you know, it's a little disturbing thinking about the idea, I mean
in general the idea, you know, people whatever we haven't, you know,
we obviously can and have but haven't had that discussion, not now
because we're a little behind. But I'm sure we'll find plenty of
opportunity, you know the whole idea that blood of a נדה is
טמאה, what does that say about sort of some natural process being
טמא? tamei I mean look, also a man, not with the same
consequences, but semen is also טמא, tamei you know, and so on
and if both of these are sort of, and you know, so
what exactly the sort of why these things are טמא tamei is
an important question, but still I think that it to my mind
it you know is more a little more disturbing the idea that
actually the uterus causes any blood that's in it to become טמא
tamei, seems to really take it to a different level. But you
know that is debated and I don't even really know how we
פסקן, pasken, I mean it's really only a פסק psak for טומאה
וטהרה tumah ve-taharah not for practical, so I'd have to see how
the רמב"ם Rambam פסקן paskens about that. But that's one point, I
want to bracket that point for now because I want to speak
about the other important halakhic aspects that were raised. One is the
idea of the מכה. Okay, that you know there's some of the
most I think heartfelt or about the most whatever very heartfelt תשובה
teshuvah literature you see around women. that have conditions. A prolapsed uterus
was very common, by the way, that they would be impossible for
them to get clean בדיקות bedikas and, you know, and what happens
and now the period of their וסת veset passes or whatever, and
how do they ever know to get a clean בדיקה bedika and
to be טהורה etc and all these very important questions about can
you be תולה במכה toleh bemakka and will the couple ever be
able to have sex and so on. And, you know, a lot
of effort is put into trying to, you know, figure out how
the woman can get, you know, can be considered to have בדיקות
bedikas and go to the מקוה and so on, even with this,
even with these conditions. So one of the factors here is like
you had this again, this very one example of that is she
has a מכה, she's got her period has passed, no checking, and
we're still going to call her טהורה even though normally we would
require checking. Nevertheless, תוספות Tosafos and the other ראשונים ask the obvious
question of like what, she's never going to have her period? Is
there any limit to that? How far do we take that? So
let's take a very quick look at תוספות. Tosafos, תוספות Tosafot's says
דמר סבר וסתות דאורייתא דהיא טהורה.
demar savar vesetos de-Oraisa
de-hi tehora. He says נראה דדווקא במרגשת שבא דם
זמנין מכה. nira de-davka be-margeshes she-ba dam zeminin makka.
Only when she sort of senses and maybe it's also an issue
about what it looks like and the color, there's evidence that it's
דם מכה dam makka blood. ואפילו הכי אם זמן וסתה הוא דהוא
וסת דאורייתא חיישינן שמא גם המכה אבל אם אינה מרגשת וכולי ואם
זמן וסתה דאי לאו הכי—I'm ve-afilu hachi im zman vesetah hu de-hu
veset de-Oraisa chayshinan she-ma gam ha-makka aval im einah margeshes ve-chulei ve-im
zman vesetah de-ee lav hachi skipping two lines from the bottom of
this תוספות—וכי לעולם לא תהיה נדה דלא קודם המכה הוה לה וסת—meaning
veset.
if you say no matter what, any blood is is always דם
מכה, dam makka, then then you know what, she's never going to
be a נדה? So תוספות Tosafot says no, if there's some supporting
evidence that it's דם מכה, dam makka, there's a sensation, there's the
color, there's some you know there's a pain that comes with it,
then we're going to say that we're not going to be concerned,
we're not going to be concerned that דם נדה dam niddah is,
it could be, but we're not going to be concerned that דם
נדה dam niddah is mixed up with it. If there's no supporting
evidence and she's bleeding, as we're going to have to say that
she's a נדה because, you know, obviously it has to happen eventually.
But that's a whole important series of factors about dealing with מכה
which is a major area. The other important issue I wanted to
raise is how do we פוסק pasken וסתות דאורייתא וסתות דרבנן? Now
again, remember, there's one idea about not having sex during that period,
we haven't really discussed that at all. Here's the key question of:
what's her status afterwards? Why is this relevant? Because it's very relevant.
Because a woman who has a regular period, the הלכה halakha is,
as we see from this, she's supposed to check during that time
of the period to make sure that she hasn't gotten her period,
that she's טהורה. Let's say she didn't check during that period and
she checks afterwards. So if you say וסתות דאורייתא, we would say
that even if a woman does a check after her period, the
couple can't have sex, they have to assume she's a נדה with
all
of the related הלכה. halakha. Right? דאורייתא. Even if she does a
בדיקה bedika and she's טהורה, וסתות דאורייתא. If it's וסתות דרבנן, then
a later check will work. So everybody פוסק paskens וסתות דרבנן. If
you wanted one of the nice proofs for that or weights for
that is the סוגיא sugya ended with וסתות דרבנן. Taking something which
on the face of it was clearly debated דאורייתא דרבנן de-Oraisa de-rabbanan
and re-read it to say everybody says וסתות דרבנן. So if you
take a look for example at the תוספות רב נחמן בר יצחק
אמר וסתות פליגי נראה דהלכה דוסתות דרבנן. Tosafos Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
amar vesetos peligi nireh de-halakhah de-vesetos de-rabbanan. And then he goes through
proving it and at the end he says, הילכך, hilkach, four lines
before the word ומר umar the next תוספות, Tosafot אשה שיש לה
וסת ולא בדקה בשעת וסתה—a ishah she-yesh lah veset ve-lo badkah bi-shas
vesetah woman who has a וסת veset. and hasn't checked—ואחר כך בדקה
ומצאת טהורה טהורה לבעלה. ve-acher kach badkah u-matzas tehorah tehorah le-baalah. So
a woman who does her check after her וסת, veset you can
go by that check because וסתות דרבנן. מיהו לכתחילה צריכה לבדוק בשעת
וסתה mihu le-chatchilah tzrichah livdok bi-shas vesetah ideally during the time of
the וסת veset as we see from this גמרא, Gemara but I
already pointed out to you the challenge of the idea of what
for an entire 12 hours? How does that make sense and so
on. But the important הלכה halakha in this is straight פסק שולחן
ערוך psak Shulchan Aruch is a woman who has a regular period
has to check during or immediately afterwards, but if she checks later
we can go by that later check because וסתות דרבנן. The last
הלכה halakha point I will make is what about a woman without
a regular period? So here רש"י, Rashi, if you remember like when
the גמרא Gemara dealt with and the idea of like when is
a woman considered מסולקת דמים, when after you know when menopausal and
speaks about three עונות onos periods and a standard עונה onah was
30 days.
רש"י—it's Rashi never explicit in the גמרא—but Gemara רש"י Rashi understands that
this idea of 30 days is a default period for women without
a וסת קבוע. veset kavua. And we treat it as a pseudo
וסת קבוע. veset kavua. So רש"י Rashi says that for a woman
without a וסת קבוע veset kavua she has to do a check
on day 30. Okay? And that's not in the גמרא Gemara's but
the גמרא's Gemara's all talking about a woman with a וסת קבוע.
veset kavua. So I'll just show you one line of רש"י Rashi
the word
right near the line on top of the הגהות hagahos here where
it says about I don't know 10 lines before the lines get
wide it said
one minute no not that רש"י Rashi hold on. Yeah
if the רש"י Rashi about five lines above the line of הגהות
מהרב רנשבורג Hagahos me-Rav Ransburg I don't know about 20 lines up
where it says
where it
says אפילו בימי נדתה afilu bi-ymei niddasah רש"י Rashi says כלומר בימים
שהיא למודה לראות דהיינו שעת עונתה או שעת וסתה. klomar bi-yamim she-hee
lemudah li-ros de-hainu sheas onasah o sheas vesetah. Her עונה onah or
her וסת. What's her עונה? onah? I thought that was וסת. So
רש"י Rashi has this idea that עונה onah is 30 days, and
that's like what, a pseudo וסת קבוע veset kavua for a woman
that does not have a וסת קבוע, veset kavua, and that has
a very profound impact in הלכה halacha that we have this idea
that every woman has either a fixed וסת or a pseudo וסת
of day 30. Okay, and with that we'll end for now the
discussion of וסתות דאורייתא and we turn back to our previous fun
discussions about the regular checks that happen before and after sex. Yes.
I just want to make sure I understood what you were saying
in how you read the position.
I understand, I'll talk about it afterwards. Okay,
משנה. בית שמאי אומרים צריכה שני עדים לכל תשמיש ותשמיש. Beit Shammai
omrim tzricha shnei edim l'chol tashmish v'tashmish. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
that you need two literally witnesses, two cloths for every act of
sex. או תשמיש לאור הנר. o tashmish l'or haner. Or, this is
assuming the couple's having sex multiple times at night. So when do
you, how frequently do you have to check? So בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says, well, either you can check in the next morning, but
you'll have to do a check after every act of sex because
as we'll see, he's concerned that if you use the same cloth
multiple times, that it'll mask over earlier checks, whatever the semen and
other stuff that comes out of the body can mask over earlier
checks. So you either need to use separate cloths or if you
want one for him and one for her?
I will
talk about that in a minute. Or if you're going to use
the same cloth, then check, then check the cloth before you have
sex again. Well, how do you check the cloth? It's night. So
have a candle lit. Okay, but the funny thing is he doesn't
say light a candle and check the cloth. He says have sex
with the you know because obviously you're not dealing with, you know,
just get out your matches right, it wasn't trivial to light things.
So he says, fine, have a light burning in the room and
then check by the light at you know and use the cloth.
Obviously Charlie's going to have questions which we're going to get to,
but anyway, check by light. But either do different cloths or check
between each time. You know, not just do the physical check, look
at the cloth between each time, because we're concerned that another check
will mask earlier evidence. So either you have to look at the
cloth between each time or you have to use different cloths. ובית
הלל אומרים. u'Beit Hillel omrim. That's what בית שמאי Beit Shammai says.
ובית הלל
אומרים, u'Beit Hillel omrim, no, here finally בית הלל, Beit Hillel, the
מסכת masechet opened with שמאי Shammai being more lenient, here they're back
to their more standard position. ובית הלל אומרים דייה בשני עדים כל
הלילה. u'Beit Hillel omrim daya b'shnei edim kol halaila. Two cloths are
enough. You don't need multiple cloths. You don't need to check between
each time. Now,
Michael asked the important question about
which are the two cloths. I will first tell you תוספות's Tosafot
read which is the easier one. The two cloths have always appeared
in the משנה as the two cloths that husband and wife use
after sex. And we're talking about the checking that happens after sex.
Okay, so what's the debate? בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you need
that that everybody according to תוספות Tosafot agrees that you have to
check after each after sex each time, even if you have multiple
times sex at night, because there's a concern that sex might bring
on bleeding. That seems to have been a concern of the גמרא.
Gemara So everybody agrees you have to check after each time, and
the only question is do you need new cloths or not? That
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you need new cloths so you have
to look at the cloth and בית הלל Beit Hillel says I'm
not going to be concerned about new cloths and therefore, and one
of the reasons תוספות Tosafot says is because you know it's very
expensive and it would be asking too much because you know there
can be a lot of stuff you have to whatever there's a
lot of fluids going on and therefore I'm not going to make
that demand and I'll be okay with just one cloth, but everybody
agrees you check after each act of sex.
So that's the way according to him one
for him and one for her. Okay, that's the way תוספות Tosafot,
says it. רש"י Rashi says that no, what we're talking about is
one before sex, one after sex, although again remember תוספות Tosafot is
really more פשט pshat because שני עדים shnei edim are always referred
to as the two things used by husband and wife after. But
anyway רש"י Rashi says we're talking about one before and one after
and that בית הלל Beit Hillel is much more lenient. What בית
הלל Beit Hillel is actually saying is you don't have to check
before you know at each time. You check once at the beginning
of the night, once at the end of the night and that's
enough. You don't have to do it each interval or whatever. So
that makes בית הלל Beit Hillel much more so lenient, not just
that you don't need extra cloths, but you don't have to check
before each time. Of course תוספות Tosafot has a very reasonable question,
which is, how do you know when's the last time? So but
okay, anyway, that's what the debate that's the debate that basically בית
שמאי Beit Shammai is very concerned and so concerned that he requires
new cloths and according to רש"י Rashi he also demands more than
בית הלל Beit Hillel a check each time whereas בית הלל Beit
Hillel is not as concerned. He doesn't need new cloths and according
to תוספות, Tosafot but then רש"י Rashi and תוספות debate whether they
need each between each time, whether בית הלל Beit Hillel agrees that
that's required. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara at the
top of דף י"ב עמוד ב'. daf yud bet amud bet. תנו
רבנן: Tanu rabanan: אף על פי שאמרו המשמש מטתו לאור הנר הרי
זה מגונה. Af al pi she'amru hamishamesh mitato l'or haner harei zeh
meguneh. Even though they said that it is you know I'm trying
to see a lighter word than disgusting, but like you know I
don't know how what word do they say for
מגונה? meguneh? Disgusting? Reprehensible, probably. Vulgar. Vulgar. Oh, that's actually not bad.
That's actually not a negative term.
Yeah, that's actually not so bad. Okay, fine, let's go with that.
Okay, even though they said that somebody who has sex you know
with a light on in the room, it's vulgar, and we'll discuss
that that's going to be a lot of the discussion tomorrow.
When is it appropriate, the circumstances appropriate to be having sex? Nevertheless,
even though that's a concern, it doesn't sound, by the way, that
it's strictly prohibited, it's just inappropriate vulgar. Okay, yes, that's a concern,
but nevertheless, there's more important concerns here about knowing that she's not
a
נדה. So בית שמאי אומרים: Beit Shammai omrim: צריכה שני עדים על
כל תשמיש ותשמיש, או תשמיש לאור, שתשתמש לאור. tzaricha shne eidim al
kol tashmish vetashmish, o tashmish lo ur, shetishtamesh lo ur. Nevertheless, either
you gotta get new cloths or you have to keep the lights
on, but I have to be able to have separate evidence for
each act. בית הלל אומרים: Beit Hillel omrim: דיה בשני עדים כל
הלילה, daya bishne eidim kol halaila, no, two cloths are not, again,
either that means one check at the beginning, one check at the
end, or it means two cloths, multiple checks but using the same
cloth. תניא, Tanya, we're talking about the ברייתא. אמרו להן בית שמאי
לבית הלל: Amar lan Beit Shammai leBeit Hillel: בית שמאי Beit Shammai
said to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, דבריכם, divreichim, לכו שמא תראה טיפת
דם כחרדל בביאה ראשונה ותחפנה שכבת
זרע בביאה שנייה. lechu shema tira tipat dam kachardal bebiah rishona vetachapennah
shechvat zera bebiah shniya.
Since you don't have separate cloths for separate checks or whatever, let's
go with תוספות's separate cloths. So maybe she bled the first time,
then when you use the same cloth to do the second check,
you'll, it'll be, there'll be a semen that'll be, you know, that'll
be that'll be that'll that'll come out the second time and cover
up the blood that was on the cloth the first time. So
you won't be doing a good check. אמרו להם בית הלל, Amru
lah Beit Hillel, so בית הלל Beit Hillel said back to בית
שמאי, Beit Shammai, so what, אף לדבריכם, af ledivreichim, you're never gonna
get a perfect check. לכו שהרוק שבתוך הפה, lechu sheharok shebetoch hapeh,
this is obviously a euphemism, while the spit is in the mouth,
meaning while the semen is inside of her, even if you're only
checking once, even if you're checking at each time, but every time
you check, there's other fluids in her body, there's semen mixed up,
so therefore every check is going to be possibly, you know, a
false check, a false negative or whatever. שמא נימוק והלך לו, shema
nimmok veholach lo, maybe the blood dissolved, so there's always gonna be
a concern that things are masked. Even if you just check, even
if you check each time, so therefore I'm okay using the same
cloth or I'm okay just checking at the end. That's what he
says. Because anyway, you're never gonna get it perfect. אמרו להם, Amru
lahem, they said, okay, you know, what's the phrase, don't let perfect
be the enemy of the good. So they
said to, לפי שאינו דומה נימוק פעם אחת לנימוק שתי פעמים. lefi
she'eino domeh nimok pa'am achat lenimok shtei pe'amim. Fine, but having, you
know, once it's a problem is different than having it multiple times.
So if you do multiple checks and each time there's a greater
likelihood that there's other types of things that will mask it, I'm
not happy with that. So that's why בית שמאי Beit Shammai requires
a separate check each time with a separate cloth and בית הלל
Beit Hillel says you can use the same cloth and maybe you
don't even have to do multiple checks.
תניא, Tanya, now, אמר רבי יהושע: amar Rabbi Yehoshua: רואה אני את
דברי בית שמאי. ro'eh ani et divrei Beit Shammai. You know what,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai makes a lot of sense. אמרו לו תלמידיו,
Amru lo talmidav, so his students said to him,
רבי, הארכת עלינו, harachta alainu, רבי, oh my god, look at what
you're demanding of us, right, literally how much you've lengthened on us,
we would say how much you've weighed us down, I mean you're
really demanding that? Check each time with new cloths between
each act and check and check? אמר להם: Amar lahem: מוטב שאאריך
עליכם בעולם הזה, mutav she'aarich aleichem ba'olam hazeh, right, we're familiar now
with this type of a thing, before it was about זרע לבטלה,
zera levatala, here it's about a concern about נדה. Better I should
make life difficult for you in this world, כדי שיאריכו ימיכם לעולם
הבא. kedei sheya'arichu yemeichem la'olam haba.
Again,
here's why the phrase הארכת, harachta, lengthened, I lengthen the demands on
you in this world so you'll lengthen your days in the world
to come. Oh, and somebody, wait,
hold on. אמר רבי זירא: Amar Rabbi Zeira: מדברי כולם נלמד, midivrei
kulam nilmad, from all of them we can learn. By the way,
I should say, of course, while I'm waiting for somebody to say
what, do you have to do this? But let's not forget what's
the general context of all of this of checking before and after
sex? עסוק בטהרה. isuk betaharah.
So which raises an interesting question, the students of רבי יהושע, were
they עסוק בטהרה, isuk betaharah, were their wives עסוק בטהרה? isuk betaharah?
You know, again, how, I mean you don't need a בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, we've learned before you can have תרומה, Terumah, you can
have חולין בטהרה, chulin betaharah, but it's an interesting point that seems
much more relevant and the גמרא's Gemara going to qualify it in
a minute, really at the next line. So let's read that. אמר
רבי זירא: Amar Rabbi Zeira: מדברי כולם נלמד, midivrei kulam nilmad, from
what all of them say we can learn. The idea that there's
a concern of checking after and according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai
a very heightened concern and so on and making clear from all
of them we can learn, בעל נפש לא יבעול וישנה, ba'al nefesh
lo yivol veyishneh, that a person who's really being פרום frum should
not have sex twice on the same night. Why? Because even though
nobody has said that, nobody said just make sure you check, but
if you have to check between each time, certainly and this works
practically according to תוספות that even בית הלל Beit Hillel agrees you
check each time, it means there's some concern of bleeding afterwards. So
if there's some concern of bleeding you then even though בית שמאי
Beit Shammai doesn't, allows you to have sex but makes sure, wants
you to go back and check what happened, ideally why should you
put yourself in that place of doubt? Why should you have sex
a second time? Assuming that the concern here seems to be reflected,
a concern that sex will bring about bleeding. So if that might,
so if that's the concern you shouldn't have sex a second time,
I guess unless you really not only do a physical בדיקה bedikah
but really look at the cloth and determine that there was no
bleeding.
He also heard that...
What? Yeah exactly now, but last word of it. רבא אומר: Rava
omer: בוא ושנה. bo veshoweh. No, you can have sex multiple times.
Why? כי תניא היא לטהרה. ki tanya hi letaharah. This whole discussion
is for טומאה וטהרה. tumah vetaharah. So you know maybe in a
world of טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah we have heightened concern, so we're
checking both twice a day and before and after and between each
act of sex and whatever, but that doesn't translate into concerns nowadays.
Okay, so for nowadays this you know and therefore and now by
the way I should say that there's actually other גמרות Gemaros that
speak of גמרא פסחים Gemara Pesachim or whatever that actually speak about
that it is important to have sex multiple times because it is
actually a fascinating גמרא Gemara which we're not going to see, but
anyway, because it actually גמרא Gemara that speaks about
the woman's, the wife's sexual needs, you know, and not just focusing
on the husband's. And speaks, you know, and obviously there's a different
biology there and about when men can get sexual gratification and it
takes women longer. And the גמרא Gemara there is very sort of
addresses itself to that. So also talks about the idea that, you
know, the importance that, you know, about even after, you know, that
having sex multiple times in the night, in order to ensure the
wife's sexual gratification. So it's actually interesting because this גמרא's Gemara questioning
it and another גמרא's Gemara actually say you're דווקא davka supposed to.
So and
for those reasons. Yes.
I just want to understand if it's about
טומאה וטהרה, Tuma vetahara, then למאי נפקא מינה lemai nafka mina in
between times, what if there was דם, בתר דאית קרי batar d'is
keri and so you're already טמא tamei, with קרי? keri? Yeah,
in that moment until הערב שמש, ha'erev shemesh, you know?
Yeah, but I guess it's a
big no no no no
no no, see, yeah
yeah yeah yeah, in
terms of extent.
Okay, yes, yes, yes, but we wouldn't say it's אסור assur either
because the whole idea is that when you're עסוק בטהרות, assuk betaharos,
it heightens concerns across the board. So it heightens also נידה Niddah
concerns. Right, if we wouldn't say it's אסור assur to do something,
okay, become טמא, be aware that you're טמא, check and find out.
The אסור assur is coming from a נידה Niddah concern, from like
a an איסור issur concern, not a טומאה וטהרה Tuma vetahara concern,
but when you're concerned about טומאה וטהרה, Tuma vetahara, that heightens your
concerns in all other areas.
And she'd be עסוקה בטהרות assuka betaharos in any way, so you
know. Right.
Yeah, but it doesn't matter, it's a general state. It's not and
this is
funny because they're like so upset about having to check, you know,
and הכל כהלכה, hakol k'halacha, you know, like so, moving on.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, okay we did that. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya
nami hachi, we taught similarly, במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim לטהרות,
letaharos, all of this is only in a world of טהרות, taharos,
אבל לבעלה מותרת. aval leba'ala muteres. For her husband she's מותרת. muteres.
ובמה דברים אמורים, ubameh devarim amurim, so you don't have to worry
about any of this for just a question about the היתר hetter
of sex and those concerns. ובמה דברים אמורים uvameh devarim amurim שהניחה
בחזקת טהרה. shehinnicha b'chezkas tahara. Now when is this that you don't
need multiple checks and so on and assume that she's טהורה and
all of these things when last time you checked with her she
was טהורה. אבל הניחה בחזקת טמאה, aval hinnicha b'chezkas t'mea,
if you came home, again going back to our earlier theme, came
home from the way from from a trip and last time he
they were, you know, he checked with her she was טמאה, לעולם
היא בחזקתה, le'olam hi b'chezkasa, you have to assume she's still טמאה
עד שתאמר לו טהורה אני ad shetomar lo tehora ani until she
tells him that that has changed. That's obviously echoing back to what
we did before. אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר
רב Amar Rabbi Abba amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Ashi amar Rav בדקה
בעד ואבד badka b'ed v'avad אסורה לשמש עד שתבדוק. assura l'shamesh ad
shetivdok. If she checks, now let's say she did a check and
then she lost the cloth. Okay, so she she didn't get to
look at it. Right. So can she go ahead what
because we've indicated that there's a concern that the sex will lead
to bleeding. Does that mean now that until she, if there's no
way of checking, it is true we said that you don't have
to check till the next morning, but there at least there's a
way of checking. If there's no way of checking would we insist
on, would we say forget about it then or would we insist
on another check and actually look at the cloth and determine? What
would we do if we've lost that evidence? Again the context is
עסוקה בטהרות. assuka betaharos. Now I should point out though this is
important because it goes back to an issue that Rivka raised yesterday.
Here's the first time that we find out within the context of
עסוקה בטהרות assuka betaharos and checking before sex and or after sex
or whatever, we find out that there's a consequence of אסורה לשמש,
assura l'shamesh, that it says what what's the phrase? אסורה לשמש, assura
l'shamesh, you can't have sex. So although right it's a concern of
טהרות taharos and only when we're in a world of טהרות taharos
do we have all these checks and concerns, one of the things
we're saying is that but until you've checked we're not gonna let
we're not gonna let you have sex. It's gonna turn into a
prohibition for husband and wife, although it starts in the world, that
was the issue you raised yesterday. Here the גמרא Gemara seems to
be saying quite clearly that once you're concerned about this in a
world of טהרות, taharos, it's gonna have consequences for allow whether allowing
or forbidding sex. So he says if you've lost it you cannot
you need to do another check and presumably look at it. So
the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רבי אילא. matkif la Rabbi Ila.
Rabbi Ila asked on this איתא, ita, if she had checked and
the cloth was around מי לא משמשא mi lo m'shamesha she could
have sex without looking at it. She we look at it the
next morning ואף על גב דלא ידעה v'af al gav d'lo yade'a
even though she doesn't know what it's gonna be. הכא נמי תשמש
hacha nami tishamesh so here too since you don't have to check
look at the cloth before having sex the second time then even
if you lost the cloth why that should be okay. אמר ליה
רבא Amar lei Rava no. Rava said זו מוכיחה וזו אינה מוכיחה.
zu mochi'acha v'zu eina mochi'acha. No, in one we have evidence we
can look at later and the other we don't have evidence we
can look at later. So if there was a high concern that
she really was a נידה, Niddah, then obviously you'd have to look
at it right away. Of course if there was a high concern
she was a נידה, Niddah, we would demand it even nowadays. So
it's really not a high concern, it's really a low level concern
and and therefore we're going to allow you to wait till the
next morning. Okay and by the way what רש״י Rashi points out
is there's also a logic to that because if it's really not
a concern about sex about the איסור issur of ביאה, bi'a, it's
really concern
about
טומאה וטהרה. Tuma vetahara. But therefore fine, but if they're not able
to check the next morning, so because it's rooted in a world
of טהרות taharos and it's a low level concern, we can tell
you you don't have to check now, you don't have to check
when you're not in טהרות, taharos, check the next morning it's anyway
about טהרות taharos you'll find out then. But that's because it's possible
to check. Once it's not possible, then we're going to make more
demands right now and even say it's forbidden to have sex in
this world of טהרות taharos before you go further. אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan, now we are done with that, with the discussion
about the whole world of טהרות taharos and so on, and now
we get to the thing the גמרא Gemara, is going to go
at great length on, we'll just read one line about it and
really get into it tomorrow, is this question about the conditions, the
circumstances under which the couple should or should not be having sex.
So let's take a look. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan אסור
לאדם שישמש מיטתו ביום. assur l'adam sheyishamesh mitato bayom. A man,
meaning, cannot have sex at the daytime when it's light. אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, some say אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna,
just he says, מאי קרא, mai kra, what's the verse? שנאמר, Shene'emar,
now interesting why he says it, we would assume it's something about
privacy or whatever, but he says this: יאבד יום אולד בו והלילה
אמר הורה גבר. Yovad yom ivaled bo v'halailah amar horah gaver.
So this is a curse in איוב. Iyov. "The day that I
was born should be destroyed and the night that it was said
that a man had become conceived." So he mentions conception having taken
place at night. לילה ניתן להריון ויום לא ניתן להריון. Laila nitan
l'herayon v'yom lo nitan l'herayon. Conception
is,
it's more likely that conception will occur at night than at the
day. So, okay, obviously that's true... What? It's pretty much true. Right,
it's pretty much true. Anyway fine, but the important point is, and
this gets really important as we'll continue to discuss, I'll read one
or two more sentences before we end, is it has to do
with, like, the גמרא's attitude toward sex. Is sex something like dirty
that has to be hidden? Why would the גמרא think that sex
has to be at night? And here it's not really a problem
with sex at all, well maybe you could say it is indirectly.
But here's a problem that obviously we want to encourage פרו ורבו
pru u'rvu and children and pregnancy and so on, conception, so better
to do it at that time. Now of course you could say,
yeah, but it also reflects an idea that what makes sex licit
is the possibility of conception. So alright, anyway, but he's emphasizing conception.
ריש לקיש אמר מהכא. Resh Lakish amar meihacha. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
says from here, בוזה דרכיו ימות. bozeh drachav yamut. That one who,
who... what? Denigrates... Yeah, denigrates, right, or maybe vulgarizes, we'll use that
term. Anyway, his ways, which here means sexual ways, should die. Now
what does it mean בזיון, bizayon, embarrassment or so? So you could
have said maybe again, maybe it's the idea that sex is somehow
dirty. But רש"י Rashi says, but רש"י Rashi interestingly quotes another גמרא
which changes it, changes it to something, again, it's often forgotten because
often people immediately associate the idea, oh it has to be at
night, with this idea somehow of some problem of sex or dirty,
but רש"י Rashi actually says no. Because there's somehow the phrase, I'll
say what the phrase the גמרא says and then a way that
I'll sort of leave you, leave you framed with that today. Which
is the גמרא says there's another גמרא that's very explicit
that says why a man shouldn't have sex with his wife in
the daytime. It says maybe he'll see something about her, you know,
in the bright light and find it repulsive. Now obviously that could,
you know, be read offensively, but I actually think that it's saying
something about, you know, that there's a, you know, there's a way
in which there's a certain amount of like not putting everything under
a spotlight. Which doesn't mean that the act is somehow problematic, but
there's a sense of, you know, about sort of what sort of
a good word... I mean I guess you know, there's a mystery
and an intimacy and it's not all about, it's not all about
the physical aspect that you want in under bright light and totally
be seen. So it doesn't mean that it has to be completely
dark, but it means that you know, it's something about connecting to
the person and not just the body and something about a little
bit of a mystery and so on and therefore that's the concern.
Now there's a big implication about that because the question is, so
okay, so what about if it's not bright light? What about if
it's a little bit light, you know, and some candlelights and other
types of things of that nature? But that is, but that's interestingly
רש"י Rashi brings that in here. It would have been very easy
to have read this line of the גמרא and say sex is
dirty and it's embarrassing and do it at night, don't do it
during the day. But no, רש"י Rashi actually says the problem is
is that it will somehow, you know, that it will, it will
lead to, it will lead to a wrong type of an emotional
reaction. And therefore we want it to be done in conditions which
are conducive and positive towards the couple and towards, you know, an
intimate relationship. So we what?
If you want to read רש"י Rashi into the line of the
גמרא, the embarrassment idea you'd say that the, you know, it's the
woman's embarrassment perhaps at being seen, at being exposed.
Okay, it could be also. Anyway we will continue with
this tomorrow.